Humans have twenty-three pairs Twenty-two pairs match in
males and females Those are autosomes Females are
X X Males are X Y Every egg
carries X Half the sperm carry X and
half carry Y The sperm decides the sex
of the child Each pregnancy is about an
even chance The mother is not the cause
of a daughter In birds the female is
Z W so the egg decides Grasshopper males
are X O If some animals have twenty-three
chromosomes and others twenty-four the twenty-three are the
males Honey-bee males are haploid grow from unfertilised
eggs and make sperm by mitosis not meiosis
A mother's X chromosome can go to sons
and to daughters A colour-blind man and a
woman with two normal X chromosomes have no
colour-blind sons because a son takes his X
from his mother